BANGLADESH UNIVERSITY OF PROFESSIONALS 
Mirpur Cantonment, Dhaka - 1216 

Preliminary Problem Statement 

Smart Campus Energy Optimization Challenge 
LLM-Assisted Operator Directive Interpretation 
Online Preliminary Round 

Item 
Round 

Round Window 
Challenge Type 
Required Service 
Health Endpoint 
Main Endpoint 
Planning Horizon 
Operator Notes 
Response Format 

Details 
Online Preliminary 

7:00 PM - 11:00 PM (4 hours) 
LLM-assisted energy scheduling and optimization 
Deployed Public HTTP API 
GET /health 
POST /optimize-energy 
24 hourly intervals 
1-3 natural-language notes per scenario 
Structured JSON 

All scenarios and operator notes are synthetic. No live campus, utility, billing, or personal data is required. 

 
 
BUP CSE Fest 2026 Hackathon Preliminary Problem Statement 

00.  How to Use This Statement 
This document is the canonical specification for the preliminary challenge behavior, API contract, operator-note 
interpretation, optimization rules, and validation requirements. 

IMPORTANT: Deployment, repository, submission, performance, scoring, tie-break, and general participation rules 
remain defined in the separate Participant Guide & Evaluation Rubric. 

Participant document pack 
Document 

Problem Statement (this document) 

Participant Guide & Evaluation Rubric 

Public Sample Cases JSON 

Inside this statement 
Section 
01-03 
04-05 
06-07 
08 
09 
10 
11 
12 

Purpose 
Defines the scenario, operator-note interpretation, API 
schema, optimization rules, and validity requirements. 
Defines deployment, testing, submission, scoring, penalties, 
and tie-break rules. 
Provides worked scenarios for local validation. Public cases 
are not the hidden judge set. 

Contents 
Scenario, system goal, and end-to-end flow 
Operator directives, clauses, and optimization objective 
API contract and request schema 
LLM interpretation guardrails 
Battery and energy-accounting rules 
Response schema 
Exact validation and hidden evaluation 
Canonical specification note 

01.  The Scenario 
BUP is operating a smart campus using electricity purchased from the grid, rooftop solar generation, and a battery 
energy storage system. Campus demand, solar availability, and grid tariff vary throughout the day. 
The next 24 hours of demand, solar generation, and grid tariff are already provided. In addition, campus operators 
may send short natural-language notes describing temporary operating conditions that affect the same 24-hour 
schedule. 
Your service must understand the notes, convert relevant instructions into structured directives, apply those 
directives to the optimization problem, and return a valid low-cost operating plan. 

02.  What You Are Building 
Build one HTTP API service that receives a 24-hour energy scenario plus operator notes and returns both a 
machine-checkable interpretation of those notes and the final 24-hour energy schedule. 
ò  Interpret every operator note using an LLM or other language-capable generative model. 
ò  Convert relevant notes into one of the supported directive types. 
ò  Mark irrelevant notes as no_op instead of inventing an energy rule. 
ò  Validate the interpreted directives before sending them to the optimizer. 
ò  Produce a valid schedule that satisfies the normal GridWise rules and every applicable directive. 
ò  Minimize total grid electricity cost after correctness is satisfied. 

LLM REQUIREMENT: The language model must be part of the operator-note interpretation path. Using an LLM only 
for plan_summary, documentation, or cosmetic text does not satisfy this requirement. 

Dept. of CSE, BUP     2     fest.bupcopc.tech 

 
 
 
 
BUP CSE Fest 2026 Hackathon Preliminary Problem Statement 

03.  End-to-End Processing Flow 
The LLM understands human language; deterministic code validates the interpretation; the optimizer performs the 
mathematical scheduling. 

CORE IDEA: Human notes are not directly trusted as math. They are first converted to a fixed structured format, 
checked by guardrails, and only then applied to the optimization model. 

04.  Operator Notes & Supported Directives 
Each scenario contains 1-3 operator notes. Some notes affect the current schedule; others are realistic distractors 
and must be ignored. Hidden cases may express the same directive using different wording. 
4.1 Supported directive types 
Directive type 
solar_reduction 

minimum_battery_reserve 

no_charge_window 

no_discharge_window 

max_grid_window 

no_op 

Meaning 
Reduce usable solar during specific hours. 
Keep battery energy at or above a required 
level. 
Battery charging is unavailable during 
specific hours. 
Battery discharging is unavailable during 
specific hours. 
Grid import may not exceed a stated 
amount during specific hours. 
The note does not affect the current 24-hour 
energy schedule. 

Required structured_adjustment 
{"hours":[...], "factor": number} 
{"hours":[...], "minimum_energy_kwh": 
number} 

{"hours":[...]} 

{"hours":[...]} 

{"hours":[...], "max_grid_kwh": number} 

null 

4.2 Simple examples 
Operator note 
"Solar output will drop to about 20% from 1 PM to 3 PM." 
"Do not charge the battery between 2 PM and 4 PM." 

Expected interpretation 
solar_reduction; hours [13,14]; factor 0.2 
no_charge_window; hours [14,15] 

"Keep at least 120 kWh in reserve from 6 PM until 9 
PM." 
"The cafeteria menu changes tomorrow." 

minimum_battery_reserve; hours [18,19,20]; 120 
kWh 
no_op 

05.  Clauses & Optimization Task 
5.1 Operator-note clauses 
ò  Every operator note must produce exactly one directive_interpretation entry. Entries must be returned in note_index 
order: 0, 1, ... N-1. 
ò  Only the directive types listed in Section 04 are accepted. 
ò  Relevant notes must be applied to the optimization before scheduling. 
ò  Irrelevant notes must use applies = false, directive_type = no_op, and structured_adjustment = null. 
ò  The same directive may appear in different wording in hidden cases. 
ò  Time windows use whole-hour intervals. The start hour is included and the end hour is excluded: 1 PM to 3 PM means 
hours [13,14]. 

Dept. of CSE, BUP     3     fest.bupcopc.tech 

 
 
 
BUP CSE Fest 2026 Hackathon Preliminary Problem Statement 

ò  The LLM must not invent demand, solar, tariff, battery limits, or unsupported directive types. 
ò  A schedule that interprets a note correctly but does not apply it is still incorrect. 
ò  For every non-no_op directive, applies must be true. no_op is the only directive allowed with applies = 
false. 

ò  Every hours array inside structured_adjustment must contain unique integers from 0 through 23 in 
ascending order. 

ò  For solar_reduction, factor means the usable fraction that remains. Example: an 80% reduction means 
factor = 0.2. 

ò  Organizer valid scoring scenarios are feasible and will not require mutually contradictory hard directives to 
be satisfied at the same time. 

5.2 Optimization objective 
After applying all valid directive adjustments, minimize the total cost of grid electricity over the 24-hour horizon: 
total_cost_bdt = SUM(grid_kwh[h] * tariff_bdt_per_kwh[h])  for h = 0..23 
Lower cost is better, but a low-cost schedule is invalid if it breaks any energy, battery, or operator-directive rule. 
5.3 How directives change the math 
Directive 

Deterministic effect used by the optimizer 
effective_solar[h] = original_solar[h] * factor for 
each listed hour. 

battery_energy_after_kwh[h] >= max(base 
minimum_energy_kwh, directive 
minimum_energy_kwh) for each listed hour. 
battery charge amount = 0 in the listed hours. 
battery discharge amount = 0 in the listed hours. 
grid_kwh[h] <= max_grid_kwh in the listed hours. 
No change to the optimization model. 

06.  API Contract 
The judge harness exercises only the endpoints below. Endpoint names must match exactly. 
Endpoint 

Requirement 
Return HTTP 200 with a JSON object containing status = 
"ok" when the service is ready. 
Accept one scenario JSON object and return one 
interpretation + optimization-plan JSON object. 

solar_reduction 

minimum_battery_reserve 

no_charge_window 
no_discharge_window 
max_grid_window 
no_op 

GET /health 

POST /optimize-energy 

6.1 HTTP response codes 
Code 

200 

400 
422 

500 

6.2 Health response 

{ 
  "status": "ok" 
} 

Meaning 
Successful health response or successful optimization 
response. 
Malformed JSON or structurally invalid request. 
Optional: semantically invalid but well-formed request. 
Controlled internal error. Do not expose secrets or raw stack 
traces. 

Dept. of CSE, BUP     4     fest.bupcopc.tech 

 
BUP CSE Fest 2026 Hackathon Preliminary Problem Statement 

07.  Request Schema 
POST /optimize-energy accepts one JSON object. The hours array must contain exactly 24 entries for hours 0 
through 23. operator_notes must contain 1-3 non-empty natural-language strings, each referring to the same 
24-hour scenario. 
7.1 Top-level fields 
Field 
scenario_id 

Type 
string 

Requirement 
Unique synthetic scenario identifier. 
Natural-language campus operator notes 
to interpret. 
Hourly demand, solar availability, and grid 
tariff. 
Battery capacity, starting energy, reserve, 
and hourly limits. 

Meaning 
Unique integer from 0 to 23. 
Campus demand that must be supplied in 
this hour. 
Base solar energy available before 
operator-note adjustments. 
Grid electricity price for this hour. 

Meaning 
Maximum energy the battery can store. 
Battery energy at the start of hour 0. 
Base reserve level the battery must never go below. 
Maximum energy that may be added in one hour. 
Maximum energy that may be removed in one hour. 

operator_notes 

array[1..3] of string 

array[24] 

object 

Type 
integer 

number 

number 

number 

hours 

battery 

7.2 Hour entry 
Field 
hour 

demand_kwh 

solar_kwh 

tariff_bdt_per_kwh 
7.3 Battery object 
Field 
capacity_kwh 
initial_energy_kwh 
minimum_energy_kwh 
max_charge_kwh_per_hour 
max_discharge_kwh_per_hour 
7.4 Example request shape 

{ 
  "scenario_id": "GRID-101", 
  "operator_notes": [ 
    "Solar output will drop to about 20% from 1 PM to 3 PM.", 
    "Do not charge the battery between 2 PM and 4 PM.", 
    "The cafeteria menu changes tomorrow." 
  ], 
  "hours": [ 
    {"hour": 0, "demand_kwh": 180, "solar_kwh": 0, "tariff_bdt_per_kwh": 7}, 
    ... 22 more hourly entries ..., 
    {"hour": 23, "demand_kwh": 200, "solar_kwh": 0, "tariff_bdt_per_kwh": 9} 
  ], 
  "battery": { 
    "capacity_kwh": 500, 
    "initial_energy_kwh": 200, 
    "minimum_energy_kwh": 50, 
    "max_charge_kwh_per_hour": 100, 
    "max_discharge_kwh_per_hour": 100 
  } 
} 

08.  LLM Interpretation Guardrails 
LLM output must be treated as untrusted structured data until deterministic validation passes. 
Guardrail 
Allowed types 

Requirement 
directive_type must be one of the values in Section 04. 

Dept. of CSE, BUP     5     fest.bupcopc.tech 

 
Guardrail 

Note mapping 

Hours 

Solar factor 

Battery reserve 

Grid cap 

No invention 

Final replay 

applies semantics 

Feasible judge scenarios 

BUP CSE Fest 2026 Hackathon Preliminary Problem Statement 

Requirement 
note_index must identify an existing operator note and each 
note must appear once. 
Every listed hour must be a unique integer from 0 
through 23, returned in ascending order. 
For solar_reduction, factor must be between 0 and 1 inclusive. 
Reserve values must be finite, non-negative, and not exceed 
battery capacity. 
max_grid_kwh must be finite and non-negative. 
The interpretation may not change base demand, tariff, or 
battery parameters unless a supported directive explicitly allows 
it. 
The completed schedule is replayed after optimization to verify 
every extracted directive was actually followed. 
For no_op: applies = false and 
structured_adjustment = null. For every other 
directive: applies = true and structured_adjustment 
must match the required shape in Section 04. 
Valid organizer scoring scenarios will have a 
feasible ground-truth interpretation and will not 
require contradictory hard directives. 

SAFE FAILURE: If the LLM returns malformed or unsupported structured output, the service must handle it in a 
controlled way. The service must not silently invent a new directive type or crash. 

09.  Battery & Energy Rules 
The existing GridWise energy rules remain unchanged. The judge independently replays the final schedule hour by 
hour using the effective solar and any additional operator directives. 
9.1 Battery state 

charge:    E_after = E_before + battery_kwh 
discharge: E_after = E_before - battery_kwh 
idle:      E_after = E_before and battery_kwh = 0 
9.2 Battery bounds 
minimum_energy_kwh <= E_after <= capacity_kwh 
If a minimum_battery_reserve directive is active, its reserve may be higher than the base minimum for those hours. 
9.3 Hourly charge/discharge limits 

if action = charge:    battery_kwh <= max_charge_kwh_per_hour 
if action = discharge: battery_kwh <= max_discharge_kwh_per_hour 
9.4 Solar usage 
0 <= solar_used_kwh <= effective_solar_kwh for that hour 
Unused solar is curtailed. Grid export is not part of this challenge. 
9.5 Energy balance 

grid_kwh + solar_used_kwh + battery_discharge_kwh 
= 
demand_kwh + battery_charge_kwh 
9.6 End-of-day battery neutrality 

final battery_energy_after_kwh = initial_energy_kwh 

Dept. of CSE, BUP     6     fest.bupcopc.tech 

 
 
BUP CSE Fest 2026 Hackathon Preliminary Problem Statement 

WHY THIS RULE EXISTS: The starting battery may shift energy between hours, but it cannot be consumed as a 
free one-time source by ending the day at a lower state of charge. 

10.  Response Schema 
A successful POST /optimize-energy response must include both the operator-note interpretation and the final 
24-hour schedule. 
10.1 Top-level response fields 
Field 
scenario_id 

Type 
string 

directive_interpretation 

hourly_plan 

total_grid_kwh 
total_cost_bdt 

peak_grid_kwh 

plan_summary 

array 

array[24] 

number 
number 

number 

string 

10.2 Directive interpretation entry 
Field 
note_index 

applies 

directive_type 

structured_adjustment 

explanation 
10.3 Hourly plan entry 
Field 
hour 
grid_kwh 
solar_used_kwh 
battery_action 

battery_kwh 

battery_energy_after_kwh 

Requirement 
Must match the request scenario_id. 
One machine-checkable interpretation 
entry for every operator note. 
One plan entry for every hour 0 through 
23. 
Sum of grid_kwh across all 24 hours. 
Calculated total grid electricity cost. 
Maximum hourly grid_kwh in the returned 
plan. 
Short human-readable explanation of the 
final strategy. 

Requirement 
Zero-based index of the corresponding operator_notes entry. 
true for every applicable non-no_op directive; false 
only for no_op. 
One supported directive type from Section 04. 
no_op is required when applies = false. 
Exact machine-checkable object required by 
Section 04, or null only for no_op. 
Short explanation of the interpretation. 

Allowed value / meaning 
Integer 0 through 23. 
Non-negative grid energy purchased in this hour. 
Solar energy used in this hour; cannot exceed effective solar. 
Exactly one of: charge, discharge, idle. 
Non-negative magnitude of the battery action. Must be 0 when 
idle. 
Battery energy immediately after completing this hour. 

Dept. of CSE, BUP     7     fest.bupcopc.tech 

 
 
10.4 Example interpretation fragment 

BUP CSE Fest 2026 Hackathon Preliminary Problem Statement 

"directive_interpretation": [ 
  { 
    "note_index": 0, 
    "applies": true, 
    "directive_type": "solar_reduction", 
    "structured_adjustment": {"hours": [13, 14], "factor": 0.2}, 
    "explanation": "Solar availability is reduced during panel cleaning." 
  }, 
  { 
    "note_index": 2, 
    "applies": false, 
    "directive_type": "no_op", 
    "structured_adjustment": null, 
    "explanation": "This note does not affect today's energy schedule." 
  } 
] 
11.  Exact Validation & Hidden Evaluation 
Hidden evaluation checks both language understanding and energy optimization. Teams should not assume that 
only total_cost_bdt or the free-text explanation is checked. 
11.1 Interpretation checks 
ò  Correctly identify whether each note applies or is no_op. 
ò  Return the correct directive type. 
ò  Extract the correct hours and numeric values within the allowed tolerance. 
ò  Remain robust when the same directive is paraphrased in different ways. 
ò  Return one entry per note in note_index order, with no missing or duplicate mappings. 

ò  Match the required structured_adjustment shape for the selected directive type. 

ò  Use applies = false only for no_op; all applicable directives use applies = true. 

11.2 Downstream application checks 
ò  The judge recomputes effective solar after solar_reduction directives. 
ò  The judge verifies reserve, no-charge, no-discharge, and grid-cap directives directly against hourly_plan. 
ò  Correct extraction without correct downstream application does not pass the case. 
11.3 Existing GridWise consistency checks 
ò  hourly_plan contains exactly 24 unique hours, 0 through 23. 
ò  Required numeric values are finite and non-negative. 
ò  Battery transitions, capacity, minimum energy, and hourly rate limits are valid. 
ò  Solar usage never exceeds effective available solar. 
ò  The energy-balance equation holds every hour. 
ò  Final battery energy equals initial battery energy. 
ò  total_grid_kwh, total_cost_bdt, and peak_grid_kwh match values recalculated from hourly_plan. 

Dept. of CSE, BUP     8     fest.bupcopc.tech 

BUP CSE Fest 2026 Hackathon Preliminary Problem Statement 

11.4 Hidden language variation 
The same underlying rule may be written differently in hidden cases. For example, all three notes below mean the 
same solar-reduction directive: 
Hidden scoring notes will map to exactly one supported directive type or no_op. They may be paraphrased, 
but they will not require an unpublished directive type or an impossible combination of hard constraints. 

Example wording 
"PV production will drop to about 20% between 13:00 and 15:00." 
"Panel washing from one until three will leave roughly one-fifth of normal solar output." 
"Expect an 80% reduction in rooftop solar during the 1-3 PM maintenance window." 

NO BYTE-FOR-BYTE MATCHING: Equivalent valid optimal schedules may differ. The judge evaluates structured 
interpretation, directive application, schedule validity, and recalculated cost rather than exact JSON equality with one 
reference plan. 

11.5 Numeric tolerance 
For normal floating-point arithmetic, judge calculations should treat values within an absolute tolerance of 0.01 
kWh or 0.01 BDT as equivalent unless the official judge package specifies a stricter value. 

12.  Canonical Specification Note 
For this challenge, this Problem Statement is the canonical source for endpoint names, request/response fields, 
operator-note directive types, interpretation guardrails, battery behavior, energy accounting, and optimization 
validity rules. 
The separate Participant Guide & Evaluation Rubric remains canonical for deployment, repository policy, 
submission procedure, performance requirements, evaluation weights, penalties, and tie-breakers. 

FINAL REMINDER: Understand the operator notes first. Validate the extracted directives. Apply them to the 
optimization. Then produce a valid 24-hour schedule and minimize cost. 

Dept. of CSE, BUP     9     fest.bupcopc.tech 

 
 
 
 
 

